background too i spent
about 14 and a half years in the cia
first as an analyst
later as a counterterrorism operations
officer i got bored of analysis
and after the september 11th attacks i
became the chief of the cia's
anti-terrorism operations in pakistan
in that capacity i led a series of raids
in which we captured a palestinian by
the name of aposta who at the time
we thought was the number three in al
qaeda that turned out to not be true
he was not the number three in al-qaeda
but our our orders were to capture him
so we did we captured him it took about
six weeks but we found him
uh he was uh shot very severely
uh by pakistani police and uh
and i sat with him for the first 56
hours of his uh
captivity we talked about a lot of
things in those 56 hours
the september 11th attacks poetry
religion all different kinds of things
and um and i told him
and i didn't mean to you know
to sound dramatic but i told him look i
am the nicest
guy that you're going to meet in this
experience
the nicest guy my colleagues are not as
nice as i am
so if i can give you any advice it's
that you have to cooperate
i told them your life is over but the
rest of it can be
easy or it can be terrible i said i
don't really know what they have in mind
for you
but i can tell you because i know them
it's not going to be nice
and he said you seem like a nice guy
but you're the enemy and i'll never
cooperate
so i said well suit yourself so after 56
hours he was flown to a secret prison
and after being given six weeks to
recuperate from his
very grave gunshot wounds the cia
started torturing him
now this was after the fbi had spent
those intervening six weeks
establishing a relationship with him and
establishing a rapport
and he actually began providing his fbi
interrogator with actionable
intelligence the cia said that that
wasn't good enough
and so george tenet asked president bush
to evict the fbi from this country where
the secret prison was located
and to allow cia officers to take over
in the meantime i had returned to cia
headquarters
and a senior officer in the cia's
counter-terrorism center approached me
and asked me if i wanted to be what he
called certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques
i didn't know what that meant i had
never heard of enhanced interrogation
techniques before
so i said what do you mean and he said
very animatedly we're going to start
getting tough with these guys
and i said what does that mean and he
gave me this list of 10 techniques
that were going to be used against
prisoners beginning with abu zabada
i said man that sounds like torture you
know you got to call it what it is it
just sounds like torture
it's not for me i said i have a moral
visceral
problem with it and i said but you know
what let me think about it for a couple
of hours
and i went up to the cia's seventh floor
that's the executive floor
and i spoke with a very senior cia
officer with whom
i had had a relationship i had worked
for him for
a little while in the middle east i said
what do you think of this they asked me
if i wanted to do this
and he said first of all let's call it
what it is they can use whatever
euphemism they want but it's torture
torture is illegal and he said you know
your colleagues you know what they're
like
somebody's going to go overboard and
they're going to kill a prisoner in
custody
and when they kill a prisoner there's
going to be a congressional
investigation
and then there's going to be a criminal
investigation and somebody's going to go
to prison
do you want to go to prison i said no i
don't want to go to prison i'm the only
one who went to prison at the end of it
but i said no i don't want to go to
prison i went back downstairs i said i
have a problem with this i think it's
torture
i don't want to be involved they had
approached 14 of us
two of us said no and one of the two
changed his mind and said yes
so they started torturing obazo beta
a lot has been made about the issue of
waterboarding
i confirmed to abc news in 2007 that we
had waterboarded opposite data in
addition to other things
but the cia was using other techniques
that i always thought were even worse
than
than waterboarding waterboarding is the
sense of of drowning
you have some sort of material burlap
cloth
plastic whatever over your mouth and
you're strapped to a gurney your feet
are slightly elevated and water is
poured on your face
and it makes you feel like you're
drowning it's very painful because
your your body is is tensing and
reacting and it's very painful
especially in your abdominal muscles
but there are other things that the cia
was doing like the cold cell
the cold cell is where a prisoner is
stripped naked
he's chained to an eye bolt in the
ceiling and
his cell is chilled to 50 degrees and
then every hour somebody goes into the
cell and throws ice water on him
we killed people using that technique
more than once we killed people but no
one was ever prosecuted for that
there was another technique sleep
deprivation former secretary of defense
don rumsfeld famously said
that he got no sleep that he had a
stand-up desk
he didn't even have a seat at his desk
and he would work for two or three days
and he was fine so that was not
torture but the cia wasn't wasn't
keeping prisoners up for two days or
three days it was more like
12 days or 14 days chained to that eye
bolt in the ceiling again
well you begin losing your mind around
day seven
and in many cases as my friend and
colleague brad here will tell you
in many cases that that insanity becomes
permanent
we have prisoners now with whom we use
the technique of sleep deprivation who
are unable to participate in their own
defenses
that's illegal we have laws that
prohibit this kind of thing
we chose to ignore them so in december
i gave an interview to abc news in which
i said three things
that utterly changed the course of the
rest of my life
i said the cia was torturing its
prisoners
torture was official u.s government
policy
and that policy had been approved by and
signed by the president of the united
states now george w bush had said
earlier that week he had looked directly
into the camera
during a press conference and he said we
do not torture
i knew that was a lie and then a couple
of days later he told a
reporter you know if there is torture
it's the result of a rogue cia officer
and i knew that was a lie he had
approved this
he had signed it and so i went on
national television and i called the
president united states
a bald-faced liar within two days
i was audited by the irs which has
continued
every single year since 2007.
the justice department began an
investigation of me which lasted
until january of 2012. now interestingly
enough
the fbi determined in 2009
uh march of 2009 that i had not
committed a crime
uh by going on abc news and saying that
we were torturing prisoners
the obama administration told the
justice department to reconsider that
decision
not to prosecute me and so i was charged
with three counts of espionage
in addition to violating the
intelligence identities protection act
and making a false statement although
i've never been clear on exactly what
the false statement was supposed to have
been
it was thrown out in any event but three
counts of espionage
now the three counts of espionage were
for revealing
top secret code word information
that the justice department said was
declassified
solely for the purpose of prosecuting me
and that
top secret code word information that
bought me three counts of espionage one
of the greatest crimes an american
can face was that the cia
after 9 11 was trying to kill or capture
members of al-qaeda
this is a death penalty case we're
talking about right
and they were going to be nice to me
about it and they offered me 45 years
yeah 45 years in prison for revealing
this
unbelievably close closely held top
secret
code word information that we were
trying to kill osama bin laden
after 9 11 after 9 11 again
so in any event like many defendants in
america today
i took a plea to make it go away i had
five children at home
it was the proven thing to do but
my time is over i spent 23 months in
federal prison
it just made me more
determined to fight this abomination
that's torture
this utter disrespect for our
constitution for the law of the land
you know like like people on both the
left and the right i maintain that we
are
a country of laws we're a country that
has a working constitution a living and
breathing document as some scholars say
and we need to respect that that
document
without the constitution and the
resulting
respect that we all ought to have for
human rights and civil liberties
what's the point in you know having a
country
it just doesn't seem to make any sense
to me so anyway
i promised brad i would be very short
because we're going to try to take lots
of questions
thank you for having me please fight
torture